<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-06-07T01:09:23+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A personal website </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dear ECE</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dear-ece/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dear ECE"/><published>2023-05-10T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-10T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dear-ece</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dear-ece/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/letter-write.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="letter-write" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <br/> <br/> It hasn't hit me yet. <br/> <br/> It hasn't hit me that within a couple weeks, I'm done with this course and I am going to be finished with University until, hopefully, the later half of my twenties. During my final semester, I have been a TA for a Freshman level class where I've met some bright and motivated students who all ask me similar questions regarding the ECE journey as if I am some beholder of secrets that will grant them the cheat codes to breezing through this major and college life. "What does the next semester look like?", "Why does this course even matter?", "Do we ever use this stuff?". The most common question has been: "Does it get easier?". So in my final weeks of my ECE journey, I will discuss these type of questions, writing to the program I am in through the perspective of the type of underclassman who once went into office hours and asking for guidance. I write as someone who was in your shoes- as someone who asked the same exact questions. Therefore I write: <br/> <br/> <h3>Dear ECE,</h3> <br/> <br/> You never got easier- you only got more challenging. Yes, things eased up after Junior year when you got to pick classes, but it was already too late. The damage was done, and I "took the L". I was once a Freshman who barely survived high school only on the glimmer of hope that College would be easier and enjoyable. I had heard that college was 'the best four years of your life', where you barely had obligations for classes and were overwhelmed with free time filled to the brim with crazy activities with friends as though your education wasn't the main purpose of going to College in the first place. What I quickly learned was that when you were 17 years old, you were asked to pick a major which would drastically shape your college life for four years. What I didn't know while making that decision was that most STEM degrees require large time commitments, making that fantasy of college life just that. <br/> <br/> ECE… you made me cry, you made me proud of myself, you made me angry, you made me happy, you made me anxious, you gave me great friends and bad project partners, you gave me long nights in the library, long nights in the lab- you made me feel all sorts of things. But you mostly made me frustrated- and this frustration lead to perspective and growth. I was frustrated because I felt as though I was fighting a system. In order to earn the grades and to understand the content (that I would immediately forget weeks after the course), I had to sacrifice a lot of time and energy, making it very difficult to balance school with my health and social life. Often times, the latter two would be confiscated for the sake of getting through the course load. My goal in my courses quickly went from aspiring for stellar grades, to just getting the shit done. The courses felt impossibly difficult just for the sake of being hard, taught by professors who couldn't care less about their students or the class they were teaching- occupied by their research. The first three semesters of my college experience, I had no social life whatsoever. Nearly every second was spent doing work for my courses, drawing on motivational videos from Navy Seals blasting through my ears to get through it all. Overtime, I broke down and burnt out… hard. I put my all into something and for what? For a number that's a bullet point on a sheet of paper that I give to a company so they can decide whether they want to talk to me or not? At the expense of my physical and emotional wellbeing? I soon realized that no, no its not. <br/> <br/> (I know this seems like complaining, but this is going somewhere, I promise) <br/> <br/> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/complaining.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <br/> <br/> Through your courses, ECE, I learned that I didn't want to do that type of work for the rest of my life. Staring at code for hours on end, throwing the kitchen sink at the screen trying to get my code to compile was not something I was interested in pursuing after graduation. You forced me to sit down and think what I wanted to do with my life. My Sophomore year, I was matched with an alum who was a Sales Engineer and he discussed with me the responsiblities of the of the role- one in which business and engineering were combined. The main part of the job was understanding people and technology rather than fixing bugs for a living. At first, I thought no way- no way I could go into <b>SALES</b>, envisioning Matilda's sleazebag car salesman Dad. But as time passed, I realized that the most rewarding experience during my time in the program was the friends I made and how we taught each other the material or collaborated on projects. I loved explaining things during tutoring and office hours. I realized that this was my calling but when other people asked me what I was interested in, other students scrunched up their nose at me, others tell me that I was no longer an engineer (as though it were a label we all had earned) and I had Professors laugh in my face. Through this, I learned to be me, that it didn't matter what other people thought of my career leap, it only mattered what I thought of myself. <br/> <br/> ECE you never let up. Why? What was it all for? Was it worth it? As a Senior, after doing it all, I can tell you that its hard on purpose. You're meant to endure and overcome such insurmountable challenges to learn that they weren't impossible to begin with. In four years, a program is assigned with taking 18 year old kids who have little background in the field and transform them into engineers who build applications and devices that our society is built upon. Would you want an Engineer building your car who barely grasps fundamental concepts on the subject? Would you don't want a dentist working on your mouth who doesn't understand the chemicals that they are using? The program is a monumental task and it's hard because they need to mold your brain into something new: a brain which can pick up technical concepts quickly. You aren't taught the subjects because you have to learn how to teach yourself. You're forced to understand how <b>YOU</b> best learn and how you can get through road blocks and hurdles. It's quite the metaphor for life. You're learning that you can get through anything you set your mind to. Never learned to play chess before but want to start? God damn, it will be hard at first, but so was circuits and after some practice, you got pretty good at them. <br/> <br/> But most of all, through ECE, you are unlocking things that you would never be able to unlock elsewhere (sort of). If you decided to major in Business, yeah you could try to learn about computers in your free time, but you would never be able to design computer systems all the way down to the chip and build any device that pops into your head. Just like how I can learn the fundamentals of basketball but there is no way I could get into the NBA just by practicing in my free time. Through this program, you can build anything you can imagine, and isn't that cool?! You've learned how to research things and understand the tools that you find and how to put them all together. You want to build an app that tells you how many times you've opened the fridge today? You can automatically think of each individual step that would go into that project within a few seconds. <br/> <br/> ECE, I despised you for a long time and mostly because I felt as though this was a one way relationship, one where I was dedicating so much just to get by and you never stopped giving me challenges. But through it all, thank you. Thank you for showing me that I can do it. I can do anything I set my mind to. Thank you for showing me that life is one huge balancing act where you're never going to get it right. Thank you for giving me memories of enormous belly laughs with great friends in the lab and working my tail for a grade. Thank you for showing me a passion for giving back and helping others and I wish I could do more. I wish I could do it all again and make the most of it- soak in every last memory no matter how good or bad it was. <br/> <br/> So does it get easier? Not until you're an upperclassman, but its worth it. You'll be forced to learn so much about yourself and grow into such an amazing person you never knew you could become. Trust the process and remember, being a B+ student who is developing meaningful connection to friends and taking care of their body is a happier person who is an A student who has no friends and is barely functioning mentally. <br/> <br/> Also ECE, please shower. Don't be this guy: <br/> <br/> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/oscar.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <br/> <br/> Beloved, <br/> Cole </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ECE"/><category term="ECE"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A letter to Computer Engineering]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">200 Days of Daily Training and falling back in love with Exercise</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/200-Days-in-a-row/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="200 Days of Daily Training and falling back in love with Exercise"/><published>2023-04-13T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-13T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/200-Days-in-a-row</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/200-Days-in-a-row/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/apple.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="Pepe Silvia" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Get ready for my rant... </div> </div> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h2 id="zap-training-vs-working-out">:zap: Training vs Working Out</h2> <p><br/></p> <p>There’s a reason why I refrain from using the term ‘working out’ and instead use ‘training’. Although the two may seem synonymous, the term ‘working out’ seems to refer to a self contained session, where the purpose is the single session itself and tiring yourself during this timespan. Conversely, the term ‘training’ makes it seem as though workouts are connected- where each session has its own purpose. Rather than dedicating a session to get an instantanious result or viewing it as a means to an end, using the term ‘training’ makes it seem as though the purpose of one session plays a role in a larger string of sessions that ultimately lead you to achieve something bigger than just that one workout.</p> <p><br/></p> <p>Within these 200 days, I’ve discovered this difference in mindset.</p> <p><br/></p> <h2 id="iphone-how-social-media-hinders-a-positive-relationship-with-training">:iphone: How Social Media hinders a positive relationship with training</h2> <p><br/></p> <p>And I think this prenotion sums up the mainstream mindset where exercise is a means to get something else. You do a program and gain x amount of weight which will make more comfortable in the gym and life will be perfect because people will respect you and be romatically interested in you. Once you hit that glorious 225 bench, then you’ll be big and strong. Want to get shredded? Eat less and do an hour of stairmaster daily, then you’ll look good. But that lifestyle isn’t sustainable nor healthy. People who fall into this hole end up in a negative loop of cutting and bulking, never happy with how they appear and workouts become this session of torture to change their lives. Of course with this mindset, people believe that the gym will change their life, hence they dedicate everything to it- in doing so leaving a lot of life left on the table.</p> <p><br/> <br/></p> <p>And it’s built this way because of social media as people are selling you on the appearance of their bodies. That if you do what they tell you, you can look like them too. They’re not going to show you how to lead a healthy relationship with fitness because then you aren’t reliant on them and won’t buy their products or keep up with their page where they can push supplement deals down your throat. If you think about it, this isn’t new muscle magazine. Back in the day, the main form of getting your lifting information was through bodybuilding magazines where they pushed you to buy certain supplements and keep you engaged to buy the next issue. They’re selling you that you’re not doing something like these other people and you’re not big enough.</p> <p><br/></p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/pepe-silvia.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="Pepe Silvia" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> How I must seem right now </div> </div> <p><br/></p> <p>Lifting is quite simple and influencers make it out to seem complicated because they need to push the same facts or points continually to make a career off of social media. It’s like trying to have a career where you try to teach people about the ABCs and colors. You’d have content for the first two months but eventually you run out of letters and numbers and you’re going to have to recycle or respin things you’ve already talked about.</p> <p><br/></p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bell-curve-meme.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bell curve meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <br/> It took me a really long time to see this and it was only through training daily and reading Cody’s blogs did I develop a sustainable relationship with exercise and my body. The most critical thing was dropping social media fitness. This means Tik Tok and Instagram and following only a few people on YouTube and Reddit. You need to step out of that rat race where you feel as though you need to look as good as certain people (who are probably on PED or they have no life outside of the gym and have a terrible relationship with food and their body) and explore unrestricted training. Find what you are drawn to. Find what YOU <b>WANT</b> to do, not what you "need" to do to look like someone else. Why would you force yourself to do an hour of the stairmaster when you really just want to learn how to shoot a basketball to play with pickup with your friends? Additionally, you’ll develop an healthier relationship to eating as you look to fuel your body rather than eating for a certain goal. You begin to treat yourself more of an athlete and fueling your body as if it were a machine rather than viewing food as a means of overconsumption or underconsumption for a goal. I’m not advocating to completely cut off all sources of information, just minimizing your input streams to a select few channels which you trust and enjoy watching. Training is your hobby, so consuming things on it will bring you joy, you just don't need influencers fear mongering on your insecurities so they can make rent without having a real job. <br/> <br/> Before I started this initiative, I was falling out of love with training. I didn’t feel that pull towards exercise, it was just something that I needed to do and I often over looked out of laziness. I think this is because for so long I looked at training as something I needed to do in order to fix these insecurities which was reinforced by social media. But by giving myself the space to train in ways which I was excited to do, to try new things and push myself in different ways, I found myself wanting to get a session in. Even if I only had 5 minutes that day, I wanted to make it work. Wouldn’t you prefer it if you enjoyed your training, you looked forward to each session rather than thinking that you have to work out? Wouldn’t you prefer to train in different disciplines and develop a better relationship with eating? <br/> Deviating away from social media, I'm going to advocate for daily training: <br/> <br/> <h2> Why train everyday? </h2> <br/> All this is to say that you should be doing more. Who is to say we can only train 4 or 5 days a week? Who’s to say we can’t be active on those days in between resistance training where we can work on getting more explosive, jumping higher, getting better conditioning, getting more flexible, bullet proofing your body, building up a gas tank, getting better at certain skills with a sport and more? These aren’t going to hinder your progress, but drastically improve it. If you work on bulletproofing your joints or getting more flexible, you’ll be better able to move efficiently and safely during your heavy sessions allowing you to stay injury free in the long term and improving your longevity to stay active longer in life. <br/> <br/> The final point I would like to make is this idea: if you take your 4 days of 2 hour sessions a week and split that 8 hours (or less) up across 7 days a week, you’ll make more progress, here’s why. Why do you perform the hardest movements first? Because you have more energy at the beginning of you session rather than the end where you’re fatigued. So it’s safe to say you aren’t as able to perform as well on certain movements at the end of your session. Now what if we spread your weekly volume across more days? Not only will you have more effective sets with more intensity, you’ll be able to use more compound movements than isolation or at the very least, increase frequency of your training. Additionally, if you train 5 times a week, that’s 260 workouts a year. Now if you train everyday, that’s 105 more workouts. 105 more opportunities to improve on yourself. Imagine you were competing against someone in a competition where the person has trained 40% more times than you. Seems like a significant difference, right? </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="training"/><category term="training"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Get ready for my rant...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spam Lateral Raises Better</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/spam-lateral-raises-better/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spam Lateral Raises Better"/><published>2023-03-23T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-23T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/spam-lateral-raises-better</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/spam-lateral-raises-better/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="trollface-what-is-spamming">:trollface: What is ‘Spamming’?</h2> <p>So I recently have seen a trend through the small threads of fitness videos on YouTube that I consume that discuss a topic that has gotten popular on TikTok apparently where people refer to a protocol given the name “Spam Lateral Raises” (I really hope that you understand what spamming is). Essentially, spamming lateral raises is at the end of every workout session, perform 3-4 sets of various forms of the exercise. As many natural lifters do not have big shoulders and the main way to target the side delts is through lateral raises, this has become a very popular idea to add extra delt volume to your routine. This makes perfect sense, the lateral raise is not a movement that is taxing on the body, you’re never going to get sore from a hard set of lateral raises as you would a hard set of squats. Although this is a great idea, I think you can take it even further to save more time in the gym. I’ve tried to add extra sets of an exercises everyday in the gym and sometimes at the end of a workout, you make excuses for not getting that work in and eventually you’re skipping too much for the protocol to be effective.</p> <blockquote> <p>:thought_balloon: Note: This is not an excuse to never get your heavy pressing movements in. You should still include vertical pressing in your routine AND making sure to get your rear delt work in too, not only to avoid imbalances but also for shoulder health reasons.</p> </blockquote> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/SPAM.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="spam" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <p>This concept is not very new at all. People have been training with high frequency with either high intensity or high volume for a while for lagging body parts and it really does work. It’s why you see videos on YouTube blow-up where trainees who’ve never trained their calves consistently start train them daily and see lots of progress. So I don’t think spamming lateral raises is the only thing you could do. To borrow the term, you could spam calf raises, or ab work, neck work- movements that won’t tax your CNS much. You could also spam easier variations of the 4 main movements like suspension trainer hack squats, push-ups, bodyweight rows, etc.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="how-do-i-implement-this-idea">How do I implement this idea?</h2> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/button-mash.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="button mashing meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> If you've ever played against someone who takes smash bros too seriously... this concept can also be applied to trainees as well </div> </div> <p>I will say that lateral raises are a bit different and can be one of the easiest of not the easiest ‘spamable’ movements: It takes very little effort, time, equipment and energy to add them to every single movement of your workout. If you’ve ever supersetted compound movements like the bench press with the pull-up or squats and rows, you know that it can be hard to get through. But supersetting with an easier movement is a lot easier and during that time, you can rest to return to that main movement. Something like deadlifts supersetted with band pull aparts are significantly easier to perform than deadlifts supersetted with pullups.</p> <p>What I’ve been experimenting with is after every single working set and during some warm-up sets, grab a set of dumbbells and do a set of 15-20 lateral raises with medium intensity. This may seem like a lot but it adds very little time as you already have the dumbbells on hand. If you’re in a commercial gym, you don’t need to take up another machine or more space, and by the end of the workout you would have done 10 or more sets of lateral raises. If you choose to, you can do this a couple times a week and get 20 sets of lateral raises easily during the week with little effort. What I’ve also been doing is experimenting with what I’ve been calling 100s, an iteration of the poundstone curls where you pick a light accessory movement and you pick a light working weight and perform 100 repetitions without putting the weight down. 100s lateral raises are great with a band as well, and it’s just one big set, no warming up and taking time to rest in between sets. DoggCrapp sets work well here too. So lets say you train 4 times a week, two days you perform my superset-every-movement with lateral raises and the other two days you do 100s. If you’re like me and you train everyday, on your lighter days or when you have down time, you can hit a set of quick 100s with a light band, takes 2 minutes. That’s a ton of work with very little effort or time added to you’re routine. Now that’s how you spam lateral raises.</p> <p>Also, don’t forget:</p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bell-curve-meme.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bell curve meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> _________________ </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="training"/><category term="training"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Blow up your delts more efficiently]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Be a STEM-Lord</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dont-be-a-stemlord/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Be a STEM-Lord"/><published>2023-03-07T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-07T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dont-be-a-stemlord</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/dont-be-a-stemlord/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p><strong><a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/STEMlord#:~:text=STEMlord%20(plural%20STEMlords),one%20who%20disparages%20the%20humanities.">STEM-Lord</a></strong> * /n (plural STEMlords) (slang, derogatory) * A self-important, condescending person with a background and/or interest in a STEM field, particularly one who disparages the humanities.</p> </blockquote> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/stemlordmeme.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="engineering meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <p> </p> <p> </p> <hr/> <h2 id="pushpin-introduction">:pushpin: Introduction</h2> <p>This term was first mentioned to me by my roommate and perfectly summarized an issue I’ve come across during my time at University. Surprisingly, this term has been coined by Humanities majors who have unfortunately had to interact with these people who often talk down to them as they consider their school work “more intensive” than others but the STEM-Lord can often put down other STEM majors as well.</p> <p>If you’ve ever taken a STEM class, you’ve had the unfortunate experience of interacting with this sort of person. If you ask about a question on the homework, they scoff at you for not understanding the concept as quickly as them or starting the assignment earlier. When you interact with them, they treat you as though they are wasting their time talking to you. In class, they may try to challenge the professor or ask outrageous questions that deviate too far from the material just in an effort to show to the professor and their peers that they are “smart”. They are the type of person who, when you talk to them, only complains about their workload and often puts down others for ‘taking an easy major’. They OBSESS over their grades and side-eye at those who don’t achieve as highly as them. They often can be found perfecting their resume, finding the perfect opportunity to add and constantly scouring on LinkedIn. Everything feels like a competition to them. They are a hard person to interact with because they aim to put others down and try very hard to come across as intelligent, all in an effort to feel smart because that’s what their ego is tangled around. They identify with being intelligent and they need others to recognize that to foster this narrative as they battle this insecurity. But by doing so, they’re forcing their insecurity on others, putting down other people and making themselves one dimensional. Who wants to have a friend like that? Nobody.</p> <hr/> <p> </p> <h2 id="speech_balloon-why-talk-about-this">:speech_balloon: Why talk about this?</h2> <p>I can write about this because I was a STEM-Lord not too long ago. Even before University, I obsessed over what College I got into and what people thought of me. I wanted so badly to go to a prestigious University so people would look at me and think, “oh, he’s so smart and hard-working.” Freshman year, I felt badly that I didn’t go to one of those institutions I had in mind and because so, I felt the need to work harder than everyone else so I could get a certain job that could impress everyone else. It took me to start dating my girlfriend where she pointed out that everything that I talked about was engineering and working out that I realized that I was a one-dimensional person. I only cared about my career and couldn’t interact with anything outside of that. But worst of all, I did it for other people; to fuel this insecurity that I needed other people to see me a certain way so that I would mean anything. But this doesn’t have to be the case. You can be more than points on a resume, you can be more than connections on a LinkedIn page or two digits in a GPA. You’re more than the University you go to. Where you take classes doesn’t define you, just like your major or what you do in your free time doesn’t either. You define who you are, you can be so much more. So, in a way, this writing serves as a letter to my past self or anyone who stands in the shoes I used to wear.</p> <hr/> <p> </p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/stemlordmeme2.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="engineering meme 2" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <p> </p> <hr/> <p> </p> <h2 id="page_with_curl-origins">:page_with_curl: Origins</h2> <p>So how do STEM-Lords come to be? Often times, it can start out young, when kids are rewarded in school for being smart. Others tell them that they are smart, they are important because they performed well on an assignment. This external validation makes the child feel good, so they continue to work hard this way to feel that way again, to get that validation from someone else again. On the Andrew Huberman podcast, Professor Huberman discussed the study, “The Effect of External Reward on Interest and Quality of Task Performance in Children of High and Low Intrinsic Motivation” by Loveland and Olley that was interestingly conducted at Umass Amherst in December of 1979, where I go to school! In this study, the researchers split up a 24 preschoolers into two groups, one group where when they drew a picture, they received a reward and another where the kids received nothing for drawing. Then after a week, the researchers stopped rewarding the first group for drawing. What they found was that the first group of kids, the ones rewarded for drawing, stopped picking up the crayons and paper when they weren’t given rewarded for doing so. But the other group of preschoolers, the ones who never received any rewards for drawing, continued to draw because they found it fun- they did it because they liked drawing itself and not for any external reward. The problem we face here is that these STEM-Lord types grew up performing well in school, trying to be top of the class because they needed the external validation- always being told that they were smart. This is seen in most STEM majors where most of the kids select their major because they want a high paying job afterward so they can look impressive to other people. Who won’t be impressed when they make 6 figures right after graduation working for Amazon! But they secretly resent what they do. They don’t enjoy doing it because they like the major, just like the kids from the first group only drew pictures because they were rewarded for doing so. Because they resent what they do everyday, they need others to know how smart they are and to put down others who don’t have the same workload just to justify their course selection and fuel their fragile ego that needs recognition from others.</p> <hr/> <p> </p> <h2 id="thought_balloon-reflect">:thought_balloon: Reflect</h2> <p>So STEM-Lords, ask yourself: Why do you think you’re better than anyone else? Why complain about your course load to others who never asked? Why make your major your personality and your social life? Why put down others to make yourself feel better?</p> <blockquote> <p>The classes and grades you take do not make you better than anyone else, you chose your major knowing what the workload would be like, don’t continue to justify that choice by putting others down.</p> </blockquote> <p>The lesson here is to not let any one thing become your personality, whether it’s the gym, looking a certain way, drinking, hooking up etc. We as people like to put labels on things and put people into categories but you don’t need to put yourself into one. You can become a multi-dimensional person by stepping back and asking yourself why you do what you do and finding motivation in another way. You can find other passions and interests outside of your career. You can pursue developing relationships through deep conversations, this way you will have a connection to someone outside of what they can offer you in respect to your career. You’re a person with so many interests and emotions, don’t let all that be funneled into one category and weighed by other people. Be unforgivingly yourself, you just got to find that first!</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ECE"/><category term="ECE"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Become self aware of how you interact with others]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ECE Classes Guide</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/ece-classes-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ECE Classes Guide"/><published>2023-03-06T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-06T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/ece-classes-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/ece-classes-guide/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/compe-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="ece" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>One thing I am very grateful in having early in my Computer Engineering journey was having a friend who was a year ahead of me that would answer any questions I had about courses or the major itself. It helped me immensely to have someone who helped guide me through the storm, so here I will do my best to give some tips and tricks on the classes you will take as well as recommendations and warnings for electives later on for your last 3 semesters.</p> <blockquote> <p>:memo: <strong>Note:</strong> These are just my opinions based off my experience, please do not take this as gospel.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>:question: <strong>Question not answered here?</strong> Feel free to email me at colehfeely@gmail.com</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents</h2> <ul> <li><a href="#preface-points">Preface Points</a></li> <li><a href="#before-freshman-year">Before Freshman Year</a></li> <li><a href="#curriculum">Curriculum</a></li> <li><a href="#freshman-year">Freshman Year</a></li> <li><a href="#sophomore-year">Sophomore Year</a></li> <li><a href="#junior-year">Junior Year</a></li> <li><a href="#design-projects">Design Projects</a></li> <li><a href="#electives">Electives</a></li> </ul> <h1 id="preface-points">Preface Points</h1> <p>Some things I think you should definitely know early on in your journey.</p> <ol> <li>Don’t Double Major in CS and CompE <ul> <li>That’s completely BS, no company is really going to care and you’re just going to be dying for 5 years instead of 4</li> </ul> </li> <li>If you have any interest in business, you MUST take the Engineering Management Minor <ul> <li>Isenberg classes are very very restrictive and it’s a great opportunity to take classes outside of ECE and great if you are interesting in combining Tech and Business</li> <li>Isenberg classes are very easy and can help your GPA</li> <li>Downside is 5 extra classes through an already packed schedule</li> <li>I only recommend if you are coming into College with 2+ Gen Eds from College credit or consider taking some Gen Eds at a community college over the summer</li> </ul> </li> <li>If you get into the Honors College, keep it for the first two years for the housing (worth it) but consider not doing take any honors classes or do the thesis senior year <ul> <li>I know you have a high ego and you want to have that one part of your resume to show off to others but I promise your sanity is not worth it, most Honors Computer Engineers drop it</li> <li>The Classes are insanely harder than the general classes for no extra credit whatsoever and will only hurt your GPA</li> <li>You will already have your Senior Design Project Senior year and doing an honors thesis is too much work. Doing grunt work for a professor’s lab will not be fun combined with the amount of work SDP will be</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Although, I have heard they removed the honors thesis requirement for ECE honors students - Companies could not give two shits whether you are in an honors college or not. If anything, they would care about your GPA more (remember the harder classes?), and they don’t really care about that to begin with. They care more about how good you can code/ your knowledge about EE or Comp E and what projects you have completed</li> </ul> </li> <li>You are not an Engineering Major, you are an ECE major. After Freshman year, you have nothing in common with the other engineering majors. They basically become either applied Physics or Chemistry majors. Don’t do too much work with people outside of ECE because very soon, you will not be in class with them and other people will group up without you</li> </ol> <h1 id="before-freshman-year">Before Freshman Year</h1> <p>Yes I know, before your Freshman Year, you shouldn’t worry about school and you should focus on spending the rest of your time at home with your friends and having little responsibility or expectations. But there are definitely some things you need to know before heading into the course.</p> <ol> <li>Know what classes you can get credit for from High School <ul> <li>This is crucial because in ECE, you have a very busy first 3 years and taking a Gen Ed is a big time sink, getting a lot of those out of the way early on is crucial</li> </ul> </li> <li>Your first year to year and a half, you will take a lot of general STEM classes <ul> <li>These are to give you the background knowledge/ understanding for your higher level classes later on</li> <li>As a warning, these are weed out classes- in fact, the first two years are weed out classes</li> <li>Physics and Calculus are challenging for many people and forces many of them out of the major</li> </ul> </li> <li>BEFORE YOU GO TO YOUR ORIENTATION <ul> <li>You will refer to the <a href="#curriculum">curriculum chart</a> below and do the following:</li> <li>Go to your <a href="https://www.spire.umass.edu/">Spire</a> and click on courses</li> <li>Go to course search</li> <li>Look up your courses (Math 131, Physics 151, English Writing)</li> <li>Look up the professors on rate my professor and write these down</li> <li>Note the ones that are too early or too late</li> <li>When you go to Orientation, they will have you pick your classes. These people do not care about you and will make you have the worst schedule ever. But if you take these steps, you will know which classes to take so you aren’t dying in November</li> </ul> </li> <li>Each ECE class has prerequesites <ul> <li>Why is this important? If you’re looking to graduate early or study abroad, you will need to look into which courses require other classes to rearrange your schedule</li> </ul> </li> <li>Consider how important studying abroad is <ul> <li>If it’s a top priority of yours, talk to Bill Leonard(a super helpful and nice Professor) right away to see how this is possible</li> </ul> </li> <li>Consider taking a minor <ul> <li>This is only feasible if you come into school with credits from high school courses</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <h1 id="curriculum">Curriculum</h1> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/ece-curriculum.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="curriculum" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <p>Above outlines which classes you will take through your time with the major. As you can see, in Comp E, the first year is a lot of general classes, but then your second year, you start taking all ECE classes. ECE is the only engineering major that starts taking pure Engineering classes this early, other engineering majors continue to take more math and science classes until junior year. You can start picking your classes Junior Year second semester, but until then, you only get to pick your Gen Ed classes.</p> <p> </p> <hr/> <h1 id="computer-freshman-year">:computer: Freshman Year</h1> <p> </p> <h2 id="fall-semester-1">Fall (Semester 1)</h2> <h4 id="engineering-112">Engineering 112</h4> <ul> <li>An introduction to ECE where professors try to show you the different things you can do in the field</li> <li>Professors in the class: <ul> <li>Professor Wolf is amazing</li> <li>Hollot is okay but up tight</li> <li>Sequira is very weird</li> </ul> </li> <li>The homeworks will be hard on purpose and really long, I suggest going to TA office hours and finding other kids to collaborate with</li> <li>There are some specific questions mixed with conceptual homework type questions on the exams  </li> </ul> <h4 id="physics-151">Physics 151</h4> <ul> <li>This is a huge weed out class</li> <li>Kids from all sorts of majors are here and its going to be a challenge to complete</li> <li>The homeworks are all online and there are two three exams. The exams will be hard, some kids will find it very easy but don’t worry, later on you’ll all be on the same level with your courses. The exams are all multiple choice which is not a good thing</li> <li>I recommend studying a week in advance, go over the practice exam multiple times, go over homework questions, go to office hours and find a study group to go over the practice exam with  </li> </ul> <h4 id="math-131">Math 131</h4> <ul> <li>Another major weed out class</li> <li>A hack for this class is that there are 10 years worth of exams at your disposal online. All the exams have 8-10 types of questions which your exam will have as well. Practice the crap out of these questions. My goal was to get to the point that I could solve them without paying attention, which was great because most of the time I took the exams, I was falling asleep</li> <li>Find a study group to practice all the practice exams with. I recommend getting a room at the library and each of use a white board and all do the problem at once then reviewing together</li> <li>I felt guilty for some reason with this strategy, it really works for these types of classes  </li> </ul> <h4 id="english-writing-112">English Writing 112</h4> <ul> <li>A grad student teaches you basic English. You should just write well and stay up to date with the course assignments</li> <li>For a cheat code, just go to their office hours and introduce yourself, get them to review your rough draft  </li> </ul> <h4 id="freshman-year-seminar">Freshman Year Seminar</h4> <ul> <li>Literally just a class for you to meet people. Be friendly and make new friends  </li> </ul> <h4 id="gen-ed">Gen Ed</h4> <ul> <li>Pick one you need, go on rate my professor and make sure they have a good score and a decent class schedule  </li> </ul> <h2 id="snowflake-freshman-winter-break-tips">:snowflake: Freshman Winter Break Tips</h2> <ul> <li> <p>Over break, make sure to watch a bunch of intro to python videos to get an understanding of what’s going on. You should get yourself to be able to program a game.</p> </li> <li> <p>If you’re bad at physics, watch some circuit videos on youtube.</p> </li> <li> <p>Watch some boolean logic videos and solve some problems.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="spring-semester-2">Spring (Semester 2)</h2> <h4 id="ece-122">ECE 122</h4> <ul> <li>This is a python programming course</li> <li>If you’ve never programmed before, this class can seem very fast paced</li> <li>Take notes by hand, believe me its easy to just type out your code from class and hit compile but you really need to go line by line and understand what everything is doing later on</li> <li>Practice writing out your code on paper before exams, try to debug by hand</li> <li>Go to office hours if you are running into errors</li> <li>Try to debug your friends code</li> <li>Programming requires a certain way of thinking and in this class is all about developing that</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-124">ECE 124</h4> <ul> <li>I am a TA in this class</li> <li>This class starts easy and it seems like simple addition and subtraction at first but the last half of the semester picks up rapidly</li> <li>You are really going to learn through the homeworks and discussion questions, so try and follow along in class</li> <li>For exams, make sure you know everything out of the homework very well as well as the discussion and practice exam questions</li> <li>Go to office hours :grin:</li> </ul> <h4 id="physics-152">Physics 152</h4> <ul> <li>Same as Physics 151 tips</li> <li>This class is focused on circuits, electricity and magnetism</li> </ul> <h4 id="calculus-132">Calculus 132</h4> <ul> <li>In my opinion, better than 131</li> <li>Same strategy as Calc 131</li> </ul> <h4 id="gen-ed-1">Gen Ed</h4> <ul> <li>Take an easy Gen Ed here or take a class for your minor</li> </ul> <p> </p> <h2 id="sunny-rising-sophomore-summer-break-tips">:sunny: Rising Sophomore Summer Break Tips</h2> <ul> <li>Rarely do people get internships the summer after Freshman year so don’t feel bad if you don’t have one or a pressure to have one, companies don’t really look at you for internships until you are a Junior</li> <li>I recommend getting a summer job and working on projects that you can put on your resume and/or used UMass’s LinkedIn learning resources to get certificates.</li> </ul> <p>   </p> <hr/> <h1 id="microscope-sophomore-year">:microscope: Sophomore Year</h1> <blockquote> <p>:warning: <strong>This is your hardest year. Buckle up because you will struggle with your relationship with ECE until Spring Junior Year.</strong></p> </blockquote> <h2 id="fall-semester-3">Fall (Semester 3)</h2> <h4 id="ece-201">ECE 201</h4> <ul> <li>This is a math course for ECE students</li> <li>Differential Equations, Linear Algebra and Eurler’s math</li> <li>Not bad, picks up with difficulty at the end</li> <li>Highly recommend working with a group of people</li> <li>To study, again know the shit out of the homework, discussion and practice exam questions. Be able to do them in your sleep</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-202">ECE 202</h4> <ul> <li>I was a tutor in this class</li> <li>Mastering Matlab and Excel</li> <li>Bill Leonard has a philosophy and really hammers it into you through this course <ul> <li>His philosophy is called <em>Mastery</em> and it’s basically doing an assignment over and over again until you get it completely right with no errors</li> <li>Essentially his homeworks aren’t hard, but you have to get it perfect, meaning you will be submitting one assignment about 7+ times until it’s <em>perfect</em></li> </ul> </li> <li>This class is a lot of work but the assignments are easy</li> <li>My strategy was to do an assignment everyday and submit it, then resubmit assignments you got feedback on everyday <ul> <li>Do you remember that children’s game called something like “clear the yard” where two teams try to throw objects into the other team’s side and the team with the least amount of objects at the end wins? This class is basically that, you are just going to work on assignments and every time you get feedback, you submit it right away</li> </ul> </li> <li>This class is set up for you to succeed. If you get your bonus points by getting things in on time, you can get an A and be done with the class early</li> <li>Go to tutoring as frequently as possible, they literally have the answer key</li> <li>DO NOT PROCRASTIONATE <ul> <li>This class will fail you for procrastinating</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-241">ECE 241</h4> <ul> <li>This is advanced programming where you learn everything you will ever need to be a computer scientist</li> <li>So if you are interested in software, PAY ATTENTION IN THIS CLASS AND TAKE BEAUTIFUL NOTES SO YOU CAN COME BACK LATER AND STUDY FOR INTERVIEWS</li> <li>Projects are hard, exams are exactly like the practice exams</li> <li>Work on projects with a group</li> <li>Go to office hours when stuck</li> <li>Use the Bill Leonard method: work on an assignment until you get stuck, then move onto something els. Do this everyday</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-210">ECE 210</h4> <ul> <li>A lot of people struggle in this class and complain a lot. They complain because they feel like there is a big difference between lecture and assignments. Yes, this is on purpose. Like how 241 is literally everything you need to get a job in Software, this course is everything you need to get a job in EE. There’s a lot to learn and like how 122 changed your brain, this class will too</li> <li>Pay attention in class and take notes</li> <li>Use different colors for your circuit diagrams</li> <li>Practice the shit out of practice exams and homeworks, know how everything works</li> <li>There are a few rules like KCL and KVL that will let you solve any circuit. Really practice those so you can solve all the problems easily</li> </ul> <h4 id="gen-ed-2">Gen Ed</h4> <ul> <li>Take another Gen Ed, make sure to go onto rate my professor and find the best one with a decent class schedule</li> </ul> <h2 id="snowman-sophomore-winter-break-tips">:snowman: Sophomore Winter Break Tips</h2> <ul> <li>Honestly this break, just do nothing and just try and recooperate/ mentally prepare yourself for the next semester</li> <li>Get your resume ready</li> </ul> <h2 id="spring-semester-4">Spring (Semester 4)</h2> <p><strong>This is considered the hardest semester by many. This is mainly because CS 250 is the hardest CS class, let alone ECE. That’s a lot of work but 213 and 231 sneaks up on you with their assignments.</strong></p> <h4 id="cs-250">CS 250</h4> <ul> <li>Math course in Computer Science</li> <li>Literally no tips, just bite the bullet, this class is god awful</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-213">ECE 213</h4> <ul> <li>This class you learn about signals and waves</li> <li>Short exams, get ready to perform questions VERY quickly</li> <li>No new tips really, strategy is show up to lecture, and try your best to pay attention. If notes are provided, use them for your homeworks and studying</li> <li>Start studying as early as possible</li> <li>This semester was so busy, I would study a day before and spend 24 hours on just this class, do not recommend</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-214">ECE 214</h4> <ul> <li>Probability and Stats</li> <li>Most fair and easy class in ECE</li> <li>Literally no excuse for not getting an A, they put this here because your other courses are terrible</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-231">ECE 231</h4> <ul> <li>Cool class, you learn to work with MCUs and building computer systems</li> <li>Vital for your JDP and SDP</li> <li>Completely project based with a final</li> <li>Learn C here <ul> <li>PAY ATTENTION TO C</li> <li>The next semester you have a brutal C class and being familiar with C will be super helpful</li> </ul> </li> <li>Work with a group</li> <li>You’re going to be that weird carrying around a vase of electronics all day :/</li> <li>Projects will seem very difficult</li> </ul> <h2 id="sunny-rising-junior-summer-break-tips">:sunny: Rising Junior Summer Break Tips</h2> <ul> <li>Again, no one expects you to have an internship at this point. If you do, you probably networked through your parents or family friends, which isn’t a bad thing!</li> <li>Get a summer job and in your spare time, you <strong>need</strong> to study the crap out of interview questions that you would be asked and preparing your interview skills</li> <li>For Computer Engineering or Sowftware jobs, read “Cracking the Coding Interview” and practice questions on LeetCode. For EE, there are definitely some resources out there to study with</li> <li>Junior Year Fall is when you are going to be busting your ass looking for an internship and you won’t have any spare time to really study hard for those interviews, so get it out of the way now! You’ll thank yourself later</li> </ul> <p> </p> <hr/> <h1 id="floppy_disk-junior-year">:floppy_disk: Junior Year</h1> <p> </p> <h3 id="fall-semester-5">Fall (Semester 5)</h3> <p>You will be looking for an internship this semester and you will be busting your ass doing so. I recommend going to the Engineering Career Center and getting your resume perfected and practicing your interview skills with mock interviews</p> <h4 id="ece-322">ECE 322</h4> <ul> <li>This is a Linux, C and bash class</li> <li>One on the hardest required classes, if not the hardest</li> <li>The way it works is that you have a certain amount of projects and grace days (days you can submit late) <ul> <li>You will need grace days later so try not to use them during the first projects</li> </ul> </li> <li>Your Projects will be things like building a Kernal in C</li> <li>DO NOT REMOVE YOUR VIRTUAL MACHINE AFTER THIS SEMESTER <ul> <li>You will need it for other classes later on</li> </ul> </li> <li>Probably the most bullshit exams I have ever taken <ul> <li>He literally puts the most random and specific things ever</li> <li>Only tip is to use the practice exam and really know whats going on with your code</li> <li>His lectures are so terrible, he does not take the class seriously and says the most outlandish things ever, he’s laughing at how brutal his class is most of the time</li> <li>You can go to lecture and right down the weirdest things he comes out with</li> <li>“Homework Assignments aren’t meant for you to learn, but for you to suffer.”</li> </ul> </li> <li>Work with a group but try to write everything from scratch by yourself first, this will help for exams which are largely to do with bugs you would run into or random things you would encounter while doing the projects</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-331">ECE 331</h4> <ul> <li>Computer Architecture, you learn how computer chips work</li> <li>If you are interested in chip design, you should love this class, if you don’t, look somewhere else</li> <li>Very fair class</li> <li>Two projects with Assembly</li> <li>Very fair exams which are similar to the practice exams</li> <li>Gummeson is a really nice guy, if you have any concerns, go to his office hour</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-371">ECE 371</h4> <ul> <li>You either love or hate Security Engineering</li> <li>You learn about cryptography, how computers and software make their information and operations secure</li> <li>Not many schools offer things like this, very unique opportunity</li> <li>Burleson is a very famous researcher in the field <ul> <li>Because so, he doesn’t seem to care about this class and gives all his work to the TAs</li> <li>I like to say that when you go to class and see the slides for the first time, so is Burleson</li> </ul> </li> <li>Labs are hard, get ready for some long days in DooDoo Hall (which is literally a shipping container with computers in it) <ul> <li>If you are interested in these labs, take ECE 332 next semester</li> </ul> </li> <li>Homeworks are easy</li> <li>Exams are reasonable</li> </ul> <h4 id="junior-year-writing-engineering-351">Junior Year Writing Engineering 351</h4> <ul> <li>Go onto rate my professor and find the best one</li> <li>Please do not take honors, this semester will be so hard if you do that to yourself</li> <li>Most engineers cannot write or public speak, its why they are engineers</li> <li>So if you can not read off of your phone during a presentation and write at a 10th grade level, you should get an easy A here</li> <li>You can also opt to take this next semester instead</li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-301">ECE 301</h4> <ul> <li>A 1 credit seminar where they try to show you what you can do with your major</li> <li>A different Professor comes in once a week and lectures about a feild of study</li> <li>Throwaway class really, can be useful if you don’t know what you’re interested in</li> <li>My issue is that the professors only really talk about what people do research in</li> <li>Most presenters are boring as hell</li> </ul> <h2 id="snowflake-junior-year-winter-break-tips">:snowflake: Junior Year Winter Break Tips</h2> <ul> <li>You should be continuing your Summer internship search if you have not found one already. Go all out and pull all the strings you have.</li> </ul> <p> </p> <hr/> <p> </p> <blockquote> <p>:warning: You are now entering the territory where you pick your own classes and take a design project each semester</p> </blockquote> <p> </p> <h1 id="arrow_double_down-design-projects">:arrow_double_down: Design Projects</h1> <p> </p> <h4 id="junior-design-project">Junior Design Project</h4> <ul> <li>Second Semester Junior Year</li> <li>Basically ECE 231 but you write reports like you would for Senior Design Project and <a href="https://colefeely6.github.io/projects/junior-design-project/">things get very low level</a></li> <li>Write easy testing requirements for yourself when the time comes</li> </ul> <h4 id="senior-design-project">Senior Design Project</h4> <ul> <li>All of Senior Year <ul> <li>Only Engineering major that has this</li> </ul> </li> <li>Start finding people to work with early on</li> <li>Have a bunch of ideas ready</li> <li>Ask a professor you like to be your advisor ASAP during rising Senior summer</li> <li>Every SDP group literally thought of an object and put smart in front of it like smart fish bowl, smart garden, smart shoes etc</li> <li>My group got roped into a project that was harder than it should be</li> </ul> <h1 id="twisted_rightwards_arrows-electives">:twisted_rightwards_arrows: Electives:</h1> <blockquote> <p>:bulb: <strong>Note:</strong> A * indicates that I heard about it but didn’t take myself</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="white_check_mark-easy">:white_check_mark: Easy:</h2> <h4 id="ece-325">ECE 325</h4> <ul> <li>Second easiest class in ECE</li> <li>Computer Networking (how computers across the world communicate)</li> <li>I found it interesting</li> <li>Easy homework and exams</li> <li>A Must take for Comp E’s  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-597sd">ECE 597SD</h4> <ul> <li>Embedded System Designs</li> <li>If you liked JDP, take this class</li> <li>No Exams</li> <li>Only homework is to review a paper and answer questions on it</li> <li>Projects were to read a paper and give a presentation about it</li> <li>Like in Junior Year Writing, most engineers cannot public speak, so if you can talk, you should be golden</li> <li>Project was pretty cool, you are given equipment and a unique research question to replicate; <a href="https://colefeely6.github.io/projects/project-chime/">I embedded information over sound</a>  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-597lp">ECE 597LP</h4> <ul> <li>Low Power Embedded Systems</li> <li>Basically 597SD but with a low power focus and its easier</li> <li>Taught by Gummeson who is really nice</li> <li>No Exams</li> </ul> <p> </p> <h2 id="large_orange_diamond-medium">:large_orange_diamond: Medium:</h2> <h4 id="ece-332">ECE 332</h4> <ul> <li>Only projects and a final exam</li> <li>1 lecture a month that is brutally 3 hours long</li> <li>Need to go to lecture for the exam, there are no recordings or notes</li> <li>Very easy until the final project (no one finished that, everyone brute forced the solutions to trick the TAs) and the final exam (super specific and random things that relate to the class)</li> <li>An easy B+  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-597aa">ECE 597AA</h4> <ul> <li>Artificial Intelligence in Wireless Based Networks</li> <li>Super easy until the final project which was ridiculously hard, no one finished it</li> <li>No way you could understand that material, it was super dense</li> <li>Homework and Midterm Presentation was the same format at ECE 597SD</li> <li>No Exam  </li> </ul> <h4 id="cs-383">CS 383</h4> <ul> <li>Computer Science’s Artificial Intelligence class</li> <li>Lots of cool but hard projects</li> <li>Great to know how AI works, higher level CS stuff</li> <li>Lots of information  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-397q">ECE 397Q</h4> <ul> <li>Quantum Computing</li> <li>Interesting class so far, the professor is boring at teaching and is excited whenever you ask questions</li> <li>Make sure you take with some friends</li> <li>Presentation for a Midterm</li> <li>Python Projects for Lab</li> <li>Weekly Homework assignments that are similar to the class notes  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-244">ECE 244*</h4> <ul> <li>Had an EE friend say it was challenging but not the end of the world</li> <li>Don’t know why you would ever want to take a Physics class as a Comp E  </li> </ul> <h4 id="cs-403">CS 403*</h4> <ul> <li>Intro to Robotics</li> <li>Basically physics, not much to do with building robots  </li> </ul> <h4 id="cs-446">CS 446*</h4> <ul> <li>Search Engines</li> <li>Roommate had a tough time    </li> </ul> <h2 id="red_circle-hard">:red_circle: Hard:</h2> <h4 id="ece-588">ECE 588</h4> <ul> <li>VLSI</li> <li>One of the hardest and most infamously brutal courses</li> <li>Professor who made the class said not to take it, it’s too difficult</li> <li>Must take if you’re interested in chip design  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-559">ECE 559</h4> <ul> <li>Continuation of ECE 588  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-341">ECE 341</h4> <ul> <li>Algorithms</li> <li>The other infamously brutal course</li> <li>Don’t do this to yourself please  </li> </ul> <h4 id="cs-311">CS 311</h4> <ul> <li>Same as ECE 341  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-310">ECE 310*</h4> <ul> <li>I know EE’s who die Junior year first semester because of this class  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-311">ECE 311*</h4> <ul> <li>Same as ECE 310  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-570">ECE 570</h4> <ul> <li>More Irwin from ECE 322, DO NOT DO THIS TO YOURSELF  </li> </ul> <h4 id="ece-500-level-machine-learning-">ECE 500 level Machine Learning *</h4> <ul> <li>People say this was a lot of work and to not take  </li> </ul> <h2 id="no-idea">No idea:</h2> <p>I don’t know people who have bothered taking these or I can’t recall what they said about it  </p> <ul> <li>ECE 315*</li> <li>ECE 333*</li> <li>ECE 334*</li> <li>ECE 544*</li> <li>ECE 547*</li> <li>ECE 564*</li> <li>ECE 565*</li> <li>ECE 565*</li> <li>ECE 571*</li> <li>ECE 572*</li> <li>ECE 580*</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ECE"/><category term="ECE"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a guide on the course work for a Computer Engineering major at UMass Amherst]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2023 Books Reviews</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2023 Books Reviews"/><published>2023-03-03T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-books/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/books-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="fiction books" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h1 id="chart_with_upwards_trend-stats">:chart_with_upwards_trend: Stats</h1> <p><strong>Books:</strong> 6 <strong>Graphic Novels:</strong> 4 <strong>Total:</strong> 10</p> <h1 id="green_book-fiction">:green_book: Fiction:</h1> <p> </p> <p> </p> <hr/> <p> </p> <h3 id="the-murderbot-diaries-all-systems-red">The MurderBot Diaries: All Systems Red</h3> <p> </p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/murderbot1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="murderbot diaries" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Jan 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>I picked this book up because every time I entered a book store, the staff raved about it, saying it was one of the best sci-fi books they have ever read. The book was super short so I gave it a go. I appreciated how this book jumped right into it and didn’t spend chapters upon chapters world building like so many other books of the genre do. The author puts you right into the mind of murderbot and you really get to know the character and become attached with his relatability. The technology and action in this book was really cool, it painted a picture in my mind. The main issue I had was the plot was very unoriginal and the author kept leading on a twist that was anticlimactic. Overall, the character and world building showed great potential and the rest of the series shows great promise as I assume this popular author’s plot building becomes better through the series.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p> </p> <h3 id="the-thursday-murder-club">The Thursday Murder Club</h3> <p> </p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/tmc1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="tmc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Feb 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Absolutely loved this book! I would put this book as the best so far, but I’m reading the sequel and it’s even better. Osman does an incredible job building hilarious and charming characters who constantly come out with witty jokes that embody the British and Irish humor. Osman does an excellent job writing from the perspective of older people and I feel like I have grown a better appreciate for elderly folks- he really makes them out to be their own unique people with aspirations and deep feelings. The TMC is essentially about a group of retirees in England who form a club to solve mysteries and befriend the town’s police officers to help them solve a town murder. My only gripe with this novel was the plot was a little dry, but the character building and the humor kept me glued to the page. This being Osman’s first book, I’m very excited for what else he has in store!</p> </blockquote> <p>  <strong>__</strong><strong>__</strong>_____  </p> <h3 id="the-man-who-died-twice">The Man who died Twice</h3> <p> </p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/tmwd2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="tmwd2" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Feb 2023</li> <li>💫 Best Book so Far</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>What a delivery from the first book! Osman continues to develop these characters in such a charming fashion that you can’t but help fall in love with them. On his sophomore novel, Osman’s plot writing has developed immensely, delivering a story with twists and turns. A must read series.</p> </blockquote> <p>  <strong>__</strong><strong>__</strong>_____  </p> <h1 id="orange_book-non-fiction">:orange_book: Non-Fiction:</h1> <h3 id="tuesdays-with-morrie">Tuesdays with Morrie</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/twm.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="twm" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Dec 2022 - Jan 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Tuesdays with Morrie is about someone who ‘sold out to the dream’ and has been left feeling empty, returning to learn from his dying professor how to live life. A must read non-fiction book that is chalk filled with quotes to reflect on, pointing you in the direction to lead a meaningful life. Must read.</p> </blockquote> <p>  <strong>__</strong><strong>__</strong>_____  </p> <h3 id="when-breathe-becomes-air">When Breathe Becomes Air</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/wbba.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="wbba" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Jan 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>I’ll keep this short. A must read. A neurosurgeon learns he has cancer and documents his life’s journey and philosophies about the doctor-patient relationship and the meaning of death. The best writing I have read this year- absolutely incredible. My only issue was the author’s ego really shown through his writing, but nonetheless, such a meaningful piece of work. Should be read in English classes rather than some outdated ‘classics’.</p> </blockquote> <p>  <strong>__</strong><strong>__</strong>_____  </p> <h3 id="adhd-20">ADHD 2.0</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/adhd22.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="ADHD 2.0" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Jan 2023  </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>I found this book very useful. In a genre where many of these type of science-based self-help books are hard to read because of academic writing, this book uses language that is not only easy to understand but enjoyable, which I believe was the purpose. The authors, major researchers in the field of ADHD, were the first people to coin the term ADD and have made many strides in their field to help ADHD be understood as it is by the general population today. They have written eevrything out in a way where they show that ADHD is not something bad, but that the brain works in a different way and gives tips on how to work with your or your child’s ADHD. They also discuss VAST, ADHD symptoms that are induced by today’s dopamine seeking world. Overall, very helpful book and I have found some methods to help with understanding the way my brain is wired.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p> </p> <h1 id="books-graphic-novels">:books: Graphic Novels:</h1> <h3 id="invincible-vol-4">Invincible Vol. 4</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/invincible.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="invincible 4" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Feb 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>I was a little disapointed when reading this. I watched the first season of this show in 2021 and absolute LOVED it. The animation was amazing, the story was so well done out, it was perfect and it left me wanting more. So I’ve been wanting to read the series for a while now so when I found this in the library, I had to pick it up. It takes place right after the TV show which I appreciated but one of the first things I noticed is that the art style isn’t the same which is understandable. This comic has a more griddy style while the show’s art style is a bit softer and the colors jump out at you more. The story was entertaining and it kept me turning the page but it lacked any central plot- it sort of felt like a TV show on Nickelodeon where each episode is self-contained. One thing I did appreciate was that the show changed a lot of the character’s races and personalities which I appreciated, definitely made the show more diverse. This volume did a good job character building and developing relationships so I’m definitely going to continue with the series but I was definitely underwhelmed which is why is received a lower score.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="batman-vol-1-the-court-of-owls">Batman Vol. 1: The Court of Owls</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/batman-coo-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="Batman COO vol1" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Mar 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Now this was a great read for comic book fans. Although I knew the plot of this series already because if its popularity and its animated movie, I was still pleasantly surprised with how well the story was drawn out. Reading this really felt like a movie and really felt true to the character of Batman. The gritty art style wasn’t my favorite but is expected of Batman comics. There was a scene in this book when you had to interact with the book physically in such a way that described the declining sanity of one of the characters which really took me aback- such an amazing way to represent the state of mind of a character and to interact with a book. I thought some characters were drawn pretty bland, every character was basically white with black hair, wish there was more diversity because everyone looked the same and it was hard to tell certain characters apart. This doesn’t get a 5 star because I feel that a 5 star review would mean that I would really push a friend who doesn’t read comic books to read it, but this comic was still a page turner!</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="batman-vol-2-the-city-of-owls">Batman Vol. 2: The City of Owls</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/batman-city-of-owls.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="Batman COO vol2" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Mar 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>This improved so much on the first one. The art style in this one was way better (I actually took some pictures of some panes because some were so well done) and it actually addressed some of the issues that I had in the first one. This one was better than the first which was great but the villains get less scary because of the plot choice. Definitely see why this has been a popular Batman series. Only 4 stars because I wouldn’t recommend this to anyone who doesn’t read comics.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="batman-vol-3-death-of-the-family">Batman Vol. 3: Death of the Family</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/batman-dotf.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="Batman dotf" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Mar 2023</li> <li>💫 Best Graphic Novel so Far</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Now this is a comic book I would recommend to a non-comic reader. Holy cow, this book is terrifying. There is some scenes in this book where my jaw dropped, it was such so cinematic. If even some elements of this were adopted to a movie, the world would be shocked. Joker is such a great villain and the writers do such a great job of playing with Joker and Batman’s relationship in this. Best graphic novel I have read thus far and a must read for anyone!</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h3 id="invincible">Invincible</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/invincible-5.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="invin 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <ul> <li>⭐⭐⭐⭐</li> <li>Mar 2023</li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>This volume was SO MUCH better than the previous one, now I see why people loved this series. The character development is great. Great story, I’ve really gotten attached to the characters and learning where the story goes. Definitely a good read, I would recommend the series to anyone looking to get into comics.</p> </blockquote> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading"/><category term="reading"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Books I read so far in 2023]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Wisconsin Method Review</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/wisconsin-method/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wisconsin Method Review"/><published>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/wisconsin-method</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/wisconsin-method/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bugen-5.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bugen 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h1 id="speech_balloon-introduction">:speech_balloon: Introduction</h1> <p>If you’ve never heard of Eric Bugenhagen, you’re in for a treat. Eric Bugenhagen, aka the Bugez, aka Ric de la stick aka Sticky Ricky aka Stick Del Hagen was a College Athlete on the University of Wisconsin Wrestling team. After graduating, Eric spent some time as a strength coach, even returning to the team as their strength coach while trying to pursue a career in wrestling on the side. Eric Bugenhagen rose to a small popularity on YouTube about 8 years ago for his insane lifts and his intense enthusiasm. Other channels took notice of his charisma and energy, reaching out to collaborate, and Eric’s career took off from there. Eric is known for playing a type of character, getting into uploading humerous videos with stock sound effects and funny titles with his devoted fans playing along in the comments. After his rise to internet cult following, Eric’s wrestling career started to take off with Eric finally getting bigger and bigger roles in the WWE, where now he is apart of the main cast of wrestlers. I’ve been following Eric for years, always inspired by his energy, humor and his strength in the gym. He had an unconventional take to lifting that opposed what mainstream social media was promoting at the time which was to eat in a slight caloric surplus, to stay lean and follow bodybuilding routines. Meanwhile, Eric was preaching to eat to fuel your body with high caloric foods like dates, peanut butter, fig bars and even on the extreme end with eating raw garlic, onions and beets. I was always inspired with Eric’s creativity, who always sought to try new things to improve his game from weird lifts or eating pet food… (definitely won’t be trying that). One day, I said fuck it and gave his method a go. I fell in love with the style of training, it’s so much fun! Training should be fun, you should leave the gym feeling happy with this method. And at the end of the day as a normal lifter who won’t be competing or making a living from training, that’s the most important thing about exercise- it improves your overall quality of life and makes you a healthier person.</p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bugen-3.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bugen 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h1 id="collision-the-method">:collision: The Method</h1> <blockquote> <p>:warning: Warning: This method is not for beginners. It requires a couple years of experience hammering techniques of the main movements. It also requires somebody who is not obsessive about eating or looking a certain way. In this style of training, you have to drop those because you won’t be training to look a certain way and you will need to eat a certain way as described later.</p> </blockquote> <p>Eric is known for his long, 20 minute rants about one topic, but funny enough, he hasn’t described his training in great detail apart from a few details going over a simple method. So simple in fact, that it seems like he’s hiding things because it goes against what conventional wisdom tells us how to train. Traditionally with bodybuilding programs, you split your program up into training body parts once or twice a week with a ton of volume each session, really hammering a muscle in, then taking 2-3 days of rest a week. With traditional powerlifting methods, you train the Squat, Deadlift and Bench Press with different variations multiple times a week, while manipulating volume, intensity over the course of training blocks. Trainees are used to following spreadsheets and filling in the numbers, believing that the only way to make progress it to follow formulas in a spreadsheet. The way Eric trains, coined by an old training partner as the ‘Wisconsin Method’, throws all that out the window. From my research, this is the program:</p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/eric-2.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bugen 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h3 id="step-1-pick-a-lift">Step 1: Pick a lift</h3> <p>Usually, this should be an unconventional lift or something more athletic but really any compound lift that you can load heavy should suffice (I would personally describe an unconventional or odd lift as a lift that you would definitely take note about if you saw it in a commercial gym- think Jefferson Deadlifts, Zercher Squats, Trap Bar Overhead Press, etc). This lift should be something you <strong>WANT</strong> to do. This is key here that I’ll talk about later. Let’s say for example, you choose a behind the neck push press because you like the movement but your overhead press isn’t as strong as you would like.</p> <h3 id="step-2-go-to-the-gym-and-warm-up-with-lighter-weight-on-that-lift">Step 2: Go to the gym and warm up with lighter weight on that lift</h3> <p>Continuing with our example, you may do some Shoulder halos or some stretching/mobility work, then go into warm ups with the bar as you would heavy work on any program- except you include more warm-up sets to get your body really ready.</p> <h3 id="step-3-work-up-to-a-pr">Step 3: Work up to a PR</h3> <p>Keep warming up with higher and higher weights until you reach a PR or a lift you’re satisfied with.</p> <h3 id="step-4-pack-up-and-go-home-do-the-same-thing-tomorrow">Step 4: Pack up and go home, do the same thing tomorrow</h3> <p><br/> <br/></p> <h3 id="step-5-repeat-this-process-until-you-stall-and-either-switch-to-a-different-movement-or-apply-this-same-process-to-an-adjacent-lift">Step 5: Repeat this process until you stall and either switch to a different movement, or apply this same process to an adjacent lift</h3> <p>Let’s say you hit a bunch of PRs 3 days in a row for the behind the neck push press but you stall on day 4. If you really want to improve your press, you could switch to something like an overhead press with chains, axle press, Z-press and so on. Then circle back to your behind the neck push press and continue hitting PRs again. OR… if you were bored of pressing, you could switch to Jefferson Deadlifts.</p> <p>Yep… that’s it. If you’ve never heard of this style before, you’re probably thinking, “WTF, there is no way you can make gains, you’re neglecting so many other body parts, so many other movements!! This isn’t optimal…”</p> <p><br/> <br/></p> <p><br/></p> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bell-curve-meme.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bell curve meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="caption"> This type of energy... </div> </div> <br/> <br/> <br/> And you wouldn't be wrong, Eric himself acknowledges that this may not be the most optimal way to train, but you can't deny the physique and strength he has cultivated through his years of training this way. Here's why I think it works: Strength is a skill. You've heard it so many times and you've probably seen it. When you train for a certain lift, you can get really strong but as soon as you stop training it consistently or you take a break from the gym, all that strength has disappeared. Your nervous system needs to become accustomed to handling heavy loads in certain movement patterns. You have the ability to squat X amount of weight, but if you aren't training for it, you can only squat a fraction of your truest potential. By training one lift every day, you're fast-forwarding that nervous system adaption. Instead of slowly adapting by training a lift twice a week over the course of months on a traditional program, you skip ahead and do it all and more in a week. When I used the Wiso Method to train Bulgarian Split Squats, on day 1 I could only bulgarian split squat 250 lbs but I had the potential to hit 305 lbs which was what I hit on the final day. I had to get my nervous system geared up to optimally use all my muscles in order to achieve what I had the potential to. By following traditional powerlifting programs, let's say you hit on average overhead press twice a week. Over the course of a 4 week training block, you hit the overhead press 8 times, each time with an RPE of about 8. With this style of training, you hit overhead press the same amount of times in a little over a week, rather than a month, and you would see way more strength gains than you would with the conventional powerlifting style. The conventional method tries to slowly improve all your lifts at the same time for a long period of time because this is how you would initially train for a meet where you hit all the powerlifts at one time. But with the Wisconsin Method, you specialize in one movement, you don’t "major in the minors" as Eric would say. It’s the difference of putting all your eggs into one basket while dispersing them among many. I'm not saying that any method is better than the other, Heck I've only been training this way for a few weeks. Just discussing the differences and why I believe I've seen so much improvement over those few weeks, the amount I would see in a year or more of training. <br/> <br/> Another reason why this works is Step 6 of the method- eating… a lot. Eric is notorious for packing in calories, like it's a second job. He preaches to eat foods with high calories like dried fruits, bagels, drinking a gallon of milk a day and more. He even goes as far as carrying around a fanny pack of fig bars. Although he has stopped drinking a gallon of milk a day and mostly follows a vegetarian-esk diet now adays, logically, it makes sense. Everyday, you're sending a massive signal to your body to grow and you're giving you body plenty of resources to do that. But what I've found is that your body **NEEDS** this type of eating. I've been **RAVINOUSLY** hungry, I've been finding myself constantly snacking, and looking to those higher calorie foods jut to hold me over. <br/> <br/> The final secret step is intensity. You've got to pick a lift which gets you excited, it makes you want to go to the gym after waking up- which is another reason to try odd lifts, ones you haven't done before which is fun to hit new PRs and try something new. To accompany that, Eric opts for a pot of coffee before training- which I don't do after kicking my caffeine addiction a year ago. Eric pumps loud metal music infused with blaring heavy guitar rifts and heavy drums. Eric can be found screaming before, during and after his lifts- an intensity which drew many of his viewers to become fans. But there's a method here. By getting yourself pumped, you are getting yourself in the zone and building up confidence to hit a lift. Eric's motto is, <br/> <br/> &gt;"It's a mindset!" <br/> <br/> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bugen-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bugen 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <br/> You have to get yourself in the mindset that you **CAN** hit that lift and you will. It's a good life lesson for fighting those self-deprecative thoughts in your head that say you can't. I know that was a long description of Eric and his method but it really needed the background to really explain what it is and why it works. <br/> # :hammer: My Personal Adaption of the Method <br/> Like many of the readers, I was also a bit wary of only performing one lift per day- especially when I've seen Eric perform accessories and preach about 100 rep lateral raises or curls in some of his rants. I speculate two things: After Eric maxes out, he performs a bunch of accessories willy-nilly just to maintain those areas OR he has two training sessions, one max session and either another where he has a second workout to get some conditioning or cardio or accessory work in OR he hits some accessory or conditioning work whenever he has a free second throughout his day. <br/> If you haven't read about my current training style in previous posts, here is the basic rundown: My only goals is to train everyday, no matter what. Minimum of 2 minutes. The Wisconsin method is another training every day method which I love. With my school demands being high and going into a career with a lot of travel, training is something that was and can be something easily neglected. This means that sometimes all I can get in on a busy day is a 5 minute conditioning session and that works great. But with the Wisconsin method, you need a minimum of 30 minutes to hit that PR. Some days, I may not have that kind of time. Here's a tip to myself and to the reader- work out in the morning. By intentionally waking up earlier and working out, you are making that time for training, before the rest of the days demands get to you. I say this, but I have yet to train first thing in the morning but it's something I hope to implement when I return to school. <br/> &nbsp; <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bugen-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bugen 5" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> &nbsp; <br/> For those afternoon or evening trainees, I suggest that after you hit a warm up lift, perform an easy RPE 6 or 7 accessory lift right after as a superset (Superset all your warm-up sets). For example, while I was training the Axle Press, after I hit a warm up for the press, I did 5-7 pullups. This may not seem like much but if you have say 8 warm up sets before your max attempt, that’s 8 mini sets of pullups, over a week is 56 mini sets and somewhere between 280 and 392 pullups- that's a lot of pullups. This is in 'Greesing the Groove style' so this is not a set that you should be pushing yourself to do. In similar style, if I have time OR take 10 minutes at a separate time of the day, I choose 2-3 accessories to perform in giant set style right after my max attempt. For example, After I hit my axle press, I wanted to work on my heavy swings and I consider my abs a weak point, I hit some landmine abs, swings and landmine split squats for 2 or 3 rounds after my max attempt. Again these weren't anywhere close to failure, probably an RPE 7 at most. These are just getting volume in, 2-3 sets of these accessories is 16-18 sets in a training cycle, 14-21 in a week. So here is what a full Cole-adapted Wisconsin training would look like: &nbsp; <br/> - **Main Lift:** Axle Press - **Optional:** Halos, Shoulder Mobility 1. Warm up Axle Press 2. Superset with Pullups 3. Hit Axle Press PR 4. 2-3 Rounds of Landmine Lunges, Landmine Abs and Swings <br/> &nbsp; For my first cycle of this style, I wanted to see how strong my Overhead Press could get. I found the axle bar more comfortable for me so I chose that lift. The first day, I hit a 160 lb press that was pretty slow. The next day I attempted a 168 press and failed, then hit a 160 lb with no belt (mini pr). The next day, I couldn't hit the actual gym so I opted to hit some Handstand Pushups (with a slight angle, not totally 90 degrees) for 3 rep PR and did some conditioning work after. The following day I hit that 168 lb PR on the axle press. The 168 felt very difficult so I decided to rotate to the kneeling landmine one arm press where I hit a PR the following day for 105 lbs of weight on the bar. The following day I hit 110 lbs. Then rotated to the Axle Z-Press and hit a 138 lbs press with a back-off set. The following day I hit 146 lbs with band for the Z-press. The following day I yet again couldn't make it to the gym so I hit 2 90 degree Handstand Pushups, did some jump rope and rows afterward. The final day I hit 180 lbs for the Axle Press, setting an all time personal record and adding 20 pounds over the cycle. <br/> &nbsp; For the Bulgarian split squats, I had no deviations, working up everyday in a new PR except for one day where I went on a run instead. Went from 250 lb Bulgarian Split Squat to 305. &nbsp; # :warning: Issues with the method &nbsp; My main gripe with the training style is that it requires you to always have access to a gym with proper equipment and an hour to train everyday. As someone who does not consistently have access to proper equipment because of shitty College Gyms nor guaranteed time to train because of a busy schedule, that is the biggest challenge. With my previous training style, every daily session was easily adapted to these variations and I allowed me to train cardio and conditioning like I wanted. With this method, it's hard to adapt and allow for time to have separate sessions to train cardio and conditioning. <br/> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bugen-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="bell curve meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <br/> First thing I have been playing around with is if you don't have time to access the gym, at home, hit a bodyweight or movement similar to the one you are focusing on with whatever tools you have at home. For example, while training for the Axle Press, when I couldn't make it to the gym, I trained the Handstand Pushup at home. I'd imagine at school if I was training a squat, I would use my sandbags for a split squat at home. The goal is to choose something that has as much resistance as possible OR, like Pavel says, "if you can't train heavy, train fast." Here are some replacement ideas for each movement: <br/> &nbsp; #### Squat: Pistol Squats (Loaded) Vertical Jumps (Seated to jumping, load up a backpack or hold some weight) Explosive Bulgarian Split Squats <br/> &nbsp; #### Horizontal Push: One Arm Pushups Dips Weighted Pushups &nbsp; <br/> #### Hinge: Swings Nordic Curls Explosive band Good Mornings Single Leg Deadlift Variations Suitcase Deadlifts Reverse Hypers &nbsp; <br/> #### Vertical Push: Handstand Pushups Depth Pike pushups Weighted Pike Pushups <br/> Pull stuff do Pull-up and row variations obviously <br/> Another advantage to this is that if you have time, working up to these will take significantly less time than a barbell, so you have more time for cardio, conditioning or accessory work. Or, you could just do a pump workout. If you take a day or two over the course of a couple weeks to not train traditional Wisco but you are still training, I don't think the world is going to spite you. Again, it’s a made up training style, make up what you want. &nbsp; <br/> # :round_pushpin: Update: February 2023 So I'm returning to this post a couple of months after I started this routine. I decided after two months after trying out this method, although it was a lot of fun, I wasn't in the right situation for it. At school, the school gym I train in &nbsp; <br/> # :checkered_flag: Conclusion The Wiso method is a training style where you choose a movement and max out everyday until you get bored. I've tried it myself and made some adaptions to my life style and training method. After being a fan of Eric's for years, I finally tried his style and I've been absolutely loving it. If you want to hit some crazy PRs, have a blast in the gym, try new lifts and eat a ton of carbs and get swole, try this method. </div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="training"/><category term="training"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I put 50 lbs on my Split Squat, Jefferson Deadlift and 20 lbs on my Press in two weeks]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Bill Leonard Method</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/bill-leonard-method/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bill Leonard Method"/><published>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/bill-leonard-method</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/bill-leonard-method/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/productivity.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="background">Background</h2> <p>The Bill Leonard method is a technique by one of my professors that I first learned from a special time-management lecture he gave during one of the online semesters over the covid period. The method served as a way to manage a large workload with ECE classes but could apply to anyone who has multiple tasks to complete at once, especially ones that require lots of brainpower where you often run into mental roadblocks or bugs with code.</p> <p>Professor Leonard started the lecture discussing the power of the subconscious mind, the part of the brain that is constantly working on things in the background even while you are doing something else. A great example of this is when you are stuck on a problem before bed and decide to go to bed then when you wake up, you have lots of ideas on how to solve it. That’s your subconscious working while you are sleeping. Your subconscious is always working even when you are awake. The BL method takes advantage of this- Here’s the method:</p> <hr/> <h2 id="method">Method</h2> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>0. When you get an assignment, immediately read it over. Don't try and solve it, just get a gist of what's expected.
1. Start on an assignment or study session.
2. As soon as you get stuck on something and you feel yourself pushing against a wall, stop. 
3. Reach out for help. Email a TA or a professor or send a message to anyone else. 
4. Rotate to the next assignment and move back to step 1. 
</code></pre></div></div> <p>By rotating to the next project, you are saving a lot of time by not turning a problem over and over in your head. We as people often times feel like we have to stick with something for hours in order to get it right on the first try. This is super time inefficient and when we take a break from something, we are actually giving our subconscious the opportunity to work on that problem, and we can make better use of our time by working on something else rather than sitting there and staring at your computer screen. Additionally, by asking for help, you are delegating your problem, essentially punting the ball so you have more information combined with your subconscious doing work in the background.</p> <p>Obviously to support this, you need to sleep and take care of your health. But essentially this is a time management tool that I should use more often. Breaks are good. Highly highly highly recommend this to any upcoming student or any professional working on projects with multiple tasks to be completed simultaneously. Especially during my time in college, there could be so much time saved by following this method.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="how-i-apply-this-in-my-own-life">How I apply this in my own life</h2> <p>I would personally combine this with a tip I learned from the Andrew Huberman Podcast where your brain’s prime time for work is two hours after you wake up. If I had a busy day, I would set up 2-3 60-90 minute periods where I can have uninterrupted deep work at different parts of the day. Before those bouts, you have complete a small task to warm yourself up. Then start your bout by playing 40 Hz binoral beats, and work on a task until you get stuck, then when you do, ask for help and rotate to the next. Try your best to stay as focused as possible for that 60-90 minute period. Once completed, stop and go take a break.</p> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thinking"/><category term="ECE"/><category term="thinking,"/><category term="ECE"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A productivity technique]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days of Daily Training in a Row Review</title><link href="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-100-days-of-daily-training/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days of Daily Training in a Row Review"/><published>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-100-days-of-daily-training</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://colefeely6.github.io/blog/2023/2023-100-days-of-daily-training/"><![CDATA[<div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/gym-meme-6.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="meme" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> <h2 id="dragon-introduction">:dragon: Introduction</h2> <p>100 Days. Wow. That’s 100 days where I made it a priority to work on a goal- to follow up on a technique I set out on. Everyday to make one step to bettering myself and improving my mental health. Although I didn’t expect it at the time, it changed my relationship with exercise and dramatically improved my overall mental health and happiness. By committing to doing one thing to improve myself everyday without fail, I was more prompted to do other things during my downtime during the day like meditate, journal, reach out to a love one etc.</p> <p>I went from thinking, “I HAVE to go to the gym today” to “I GET to go to the gym today.” Ask yourself, which do you say to yourself?</p> <p>Now before I dive in, let me discuss WHY I did this. Lets wind things all the way back to the lockdown. Over the pandemic when we were on campus but all classes were remote and the campus rec center was closed, I had to resort to creative measures to continue to train. Around this time, Cody over at swoleateveryheight.blogspot.com had an excellent guest write-up where one of his clients wrote an article about his journey in daily training, taking a page out of Cody’s book. The <a href="http://swoleateveryheight.blogspot.com/2021/12/365-days-and-counting.html">write-up</a> really spoke to me because, like me, Ben worked with very limited equipment, just a couple of kettlebells, pullup bar, a bench and a few more things. Ben advocated for conditioning training and how there is a lot to gain from incorporating it into your training. The post really spoke to me and I tried a couple conditioning sessions while I ran deload weeks but was never consistent with the sessions. I always thought it was difficult to fit it into my current routine which prioritized either strength or size goals.</p> <p>Fast forward two years and I’m coming into the second half of my fourth year of training. Either I couldn’t admit it to myself at the time or just didn’t notice it but I was getting burnt out from the same style of training. Just to give to some context (not complaining in any sort of way), As a college student with the degree I was perusing, finding time to workout was difficult to fit into my schedule if I also wanted to make time to spend with friends and socializing. In addition, the smaller school gym I workout at has weird and limited hours with only two areas to perform the big three and if the only time I had to workout that day was limited and that equipment was not available, I was screwed. Additionally, I was always bouncing between places, whether it was at home or at school or on vacation etc, I never had the consistent access to a barbell and appropriate weights to pursue the powerlifting ventures I would set out on. I would get stressed about not hitting my weights for the spreadsheet and it was all hard to manage on a time crunch. I was a little tired of training that way and I guess it was hard to admit to myself that it didn’t get me excited to train that way.</p> <p>So when I was returning back to school, I thought of adopting a new strategy to training like I did the previous year to account for my bust schedule (last year having only 1 hour workouts was a big deal to me). I was also coming off of a big mental health growth spurt and I felt a lot more confident in myself and my body, and using exercise as a boost to my overall quality of health was also a leading factor. I experimented with quick workouts before school started because at the time, that was all that motivated me to train, just some simple kettlebell stuff was all that was interesting to me. During one of these sessions, I was listening to mind pump and they just came out with an episode discussing a blueprint for exercising 6 days a week for 20 minutes. I don’t know why it sounded so simple but what they were saying really clicked with me and I remembered the posts from Cody and Ben and I thought if I were to shoot for 6, why not make it 7. And thus, my adventure begun.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="school_satchel-the-set-up">:school_satchel: The Set-Up</h2> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/train.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> TRAIN everyday! </div> </div> <p>This may be weird and I recommend reading Cody’s post on this but I removed goals for this training style. There was no weight goal for the bar or my body, instead the goal was training itself. Enjoying moving was the goal. Challenging myself and pushing myself was the goal. Doing what would make me excited to go to the gym everyday. The ultimate goal was to train in different fashions which got me excited and pushed me to improve in an effort to reap those mental health benefits.</p> <p>Although the following were styles I used, ultimately anything that got my body moving with the intent to better myself or push myself counts as training to me. This means that somedays I just went to they gym and worked on my Jefferson Deadlift. One day I played Pickleball for an hour, another I did 500 calf raises. These weren’t the norm but I literally could do anything I wanted, which REALLY got me excited to train.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="battery-conditioning">:battery: Conditioning</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/mat-fraser-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Mat Fraser's story really makes you want to get some conditioning work in </div> </div> <p>After reading posts I previously discussed, I thought conditioning would be an excellent style to serves as a new way to challenge myself and the sessions are short! Who really doesn’t have 5-15 minutes a day to exercise? When I was having a super busy day and I knew a longer weights session wasn’t feasible, I could hit a conditioning session and feel amazing after- I could even do it at home if needed. There was definitely times where it was late in the evening and I didn’t get a chance to train yet and I hit a conditioning session in my room before the night came to an end.</p> <p>I often borrowed sessions from the following resources</p> <p><strong>Resources:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Mythical’s book of bad ideas</li> <li>WODwell App</li> <li>Brian Alsruhe shredded for summer</li> <li><a href="http://swoleateveryheight.blogspot.com/2014/02/conditioning-barney-style-how-to-stay.html">GZCL Write-up</a></li> </ul> <p>The beauty of conditioning sessions is that it breeds creativity. Only have a dumbbell, jump rope and your bodyweight? You can get a crazy session in. Only have 2 minutes and a kettlebell? Your ass is going to get whooped.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="runner-running">:runner: Running</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/running-1.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Mmm yes, stock image of running </div> </div> <p>You won’t hear much of this from Cody and others. Actually, Cody and Ben cited running as something that didn’t count as a training session for them. I really disagree with this. How does 10 minutes of high intensity training count as a session but 25 minutes of medium intensity not?</p> <p>Has this happened to you? You are walking briskly up the stairs and at the top when someone starts a conversation with you, you are slightly out of breathe? Well that was me. It was kind of weird because as someone who has been consistently lifting weights for a few years, you think I would be fit enough for a few flights of stairs. But the reality of the situation is that lifting weights doesn’t make you fit. You get really good at couple movements if you powerlift or you look good aesthetically if you body build but in reality you are super unhealthy and couldn’t do anything outside of leg press 4 sets of 15. I used to run in high school and the high after a run is absolutely insane. I knew that if I brought that back into my life, it would help me out immensely. Additionally, it was exciting to push myself, to try and train in ways that are uncomfortable. In order to run, all you need is a pair of running shoes- I could do that from anywhere, continuing to reduce the margin for excuses. If I wasn’t feeling an intense conditioning session or if I was sore from the weights or if I was excited to listen to a certain podcast, I’d throw on an episode and hit the road. There is just something so special about exercising outside in the fresh air. I loved it so much that whenever I get the opportunity to, I will move my sessions outside.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="crown-knees-over-toes">:crown: Knees Over Toes</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/ben-patrick.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Ben Patrick is changing athletes and everyday people </div> </div> <p>Now I only started incorporating this style into my training about half way through. I got sucked into Ben Patrick’s videos and his book and it really got me motivated to train in a style which strengthens my joints to ensure that I could become more injury resilient and improve my health down the line. My long term goals is to still be exercising in my 50s, I don’t want my time training now to leave me broken and unhealthy at that time. Additionally, I have had an interest in learning to play basketball or join a Sunday soccer league after graduation and becoming a good athlete would feel like so much fun. I got Ben Patrick’s Knee Ability Zero and it game me yet another tool to use if I had to train in my room or with limited equipment. Not going to lie, the training was not easy, and it has been cool to be new and not good at something. After KA0, Ben said that the KOT training is once per week but I would do anything to push around a sled if I could outside of that day.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="bomb-resistance-training">:bomb: Resistance Training</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/eric-2.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Of course... the Bugez </div> </div> <p>I know a lot of readers will hate this but I have to admit it, I freestyled all of my weightlifting sessions. I know, I know, the keyboard warriors are throwing a fit right now, telling me about how suboptimal I’ve been and more. But like I mentioned before, I was pretty unexcited to train following a spreadsheet and consistent barbell training wasn’t a choice for me. Most people would be super frustrated about that, but I’ve had experience with training with limited equipment and I honestly prefer it.</p> <p>As previously and extensively griped about on this blog, I hate my campus’s training facilities. They are poorly set up and tiny compared to the amount of students at the university. There are barely any barbell or squat racks which forced me to wait 20 minutes for something to come available. Before this session, I decided that in order to train everyday, I couldn’t be waiting for equipment because I may not have time that day and I would be wasting my own time. Hence, I made the decision to ‘freestyle’ my workouts with whatever equipment was available. This meant I had the opportunity to work with equipment I may not have specialized in like kettlebell training and ring work. Again, I was making the most of what I had available.</p> <p>Most of my sessions at the gym followed two types of formats:</p> <p><strong>Format A:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Warm-up on a big lift</li> <li>3-4 sets of a Big Lift</li> <li>3 sets Dumbbell variation of big lift - superset with a pull movement</li> <li>Accessories if I have time</li> </ul> <p><strong>Example:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Warm up on Squats</li> <li>3-4 sets of heavy Squats</li> <li>3 sets of DB Bench Superset with Franco Pull-ups</li> </ul> <p><strong>Format B:</strong></p> <ul> <li>2-3 sets of all the main 4 movements (Push-Pull-Squat-Hinge)</li> <li>Lots of Supersets</li> <li>2-3 sets of accessories if time</li> </ul> <p><strong>Example:</strong></p> <ul> <li>2 sets of Kettlebell Lunges superset with Ring Dips</li> <li>2 sets of Kettlebell Swings superset with Suspension Trainer Rows</li> <li>2 sets of Kettlebell Presses superset with Calf Raises</li> <li>2 sets of EZ Bar Curls superset with EZ Bar Overhead Tri Extension</li> </ul> <p>But a lot of the time, I wasn’t able to train in they gym. Luckily, I have a sandbag, resistance bands, NordStick, DIY suspension trainer and ab wheel at home so I could always string things together at home. These workouts took format B (obviously using variations of movements with equipment I had) but I when I started to incorporate KOT training into my routine, I would have 2 superset combinations and then the KOT routine. Although I didn’t train according to a set program, nearly all my movements were the same from week to week. I needed it to be this way because when I stepped in the gym, the available equipment I could use would vary daily. This mostly included Split Squats and Lunges, Dips, Push-ups, Suspension trainer press or fly and Dumbbell Bench, Swings, Nordic Curls, Snatches, Cleans and RDLs, Press, Push Press, Arnold Press, Lu Raise, Lateral Raise and Front Raise, Pullovers, Pull-up variations, pull-downs and row variations. Accessories were arms, core, traps and calf raises.</p> <p>The reason I trained this way was to get as high of a frequency as possible. Even on a lot of my run days, I would hit a superset to get some extra frequency in, it’s really the style I love the most. You don’t need me to tell you how critical high frequency training is.</p> <p>Don’t get me wrong, I did not train lightly. The true challenge was not pushing myself too much at first because then it would be much harder to train the next day. I LOVE training hard but getting to a level that won’t hinder my performance the next days was a new challenge.</p> <p>This was the first time I trained single leg squat movements in a long time. It was also the first time I trained seriously with kettlebells and I instantly fell in love. Its so hard to describe the feeling of training intensely with kettlebells.</p> <p>Another thing worth mentioning was that I had the chance to have some sessions with the heavy sandbag and oh my, what a treat.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="bento-fueling">:bento: Fueling</h3> <div class="container"> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/strongest-eating.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="produc" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Iykyk </div> </div> <p>By training this way, I became VERY hungry. So, I simply just ate to support that. I like to keep eating simple and unrestrictive. I focused on having 3-4 meals where there was a protein source, carb source and a veggie source. Beyond that, I would always have calorie dense snacks throughout the day like peanut butter sandwiches, dates, bagels, trail mix, fig bars etc.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="book-results">:book: Results</h2> <p>It was a challenge, there were definitely days where I barely had any time during the day to train but I still made it happen. On those days, just getting some bodyweight conditioning or convict style training in got the thing done. But it was also super rewarding. I made a commitment to myself and held up that for 100 days in a row. I felt happier, getting those endorphins flowing and sense of accomplishment everyday really can improve your overall quality of life. I also made time to train in new ways which was also great to push myself in different verticals but it was also a different feeling of accomplishment afterword.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bar_chart-takeaways">:bar_chart: Takeaways</h2> <p>You can train everyday and it is probably better for the busier person. Trying to find 60+ minutes a couple times a week is harder than at least 5 minutes everyday.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="training"/><category term="training"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How I hit Personal Bests by not training them]]></summary></entry></feed>